Hey, welcome to Upon Further Review
brought to you by Cororsite. I'm your
host Paul Guettes and a lot of news to
report on and talk about in this
episode. Let's start with the calendar.
The calendar being what it is in the
NFL. There's always something going on.
Offseason, what offseason? Let's get
right to it. The Raiders on uh this week
on Tuesday, they began their offseason
workout program. Uh lots of guys in the
building getting their workouts on,
getting their treatments, things like
that. They're not on the grass yet. We
got voluntary mini camp uh April 20th
through the 22nd. OTAAS begin May 18th,
conclude June 4th. We got mandatory mini
camp June 6th through the 11th. Rookie
mini camp dates, those have not been
released just yet. But we also have some
news when it comes to roster uh signings
and things like that. They've been
really busy since uh we last checked in
and we talked with general manager John
Spitech at the owners meetings. He gave
a little bit of a clue. He said, "Yeah,
they've done some big things in the in
the offseason, but they still have a few
more things to go." Among those, a lot
of ressignings. Tristan McCollum,
safety, resigned. Center Will Putnham
resigned. Offensive lineman, center
offensive guard, uh Jordan Meredith,
he's back. Defensive end Charles
Snowden. Tight end Ian Thomas also
coming back. The big fish, the big news
of the week though, the Raiders signing
a veteran quarterback. And what better
way to discuss this and break it down
than talking with a four-time Pro
Bowler, a two-time AllPro, the 2002 NFL
MVP, Rich Ganon. And I guess I could ask
you right off the bat, why didn't you
want to play defensive back for the
Patriots or running back for the
Patriots when they drafted you in 1987?
But instead, I'll ask you your quick
knee-jerk reaction to the Raiders
signing Kirk Cousins, a guy that's been
around the league for a while and has a
lot of pelts on the wall as well. Well,
Paul, I thought it was a great signing.
I've known Kirk a long time, and I just
think you bring a wealth of experience
and knowledge, uh, wisdom, and really a
level of professionalism that is so
important for that quarterback room,
especially when you're going to try to
develop a young quarterback. And I think
when you look at Kirk's body of work,
everywhere he has been, um, he has been
a pretty consistent player really week
in and week out. I think you're talking
about a guy that has 167 career starts.
He's thrown for almost 45,000 yards and
almost 300 touchdowns. So, uh, you know,
you love that about him. Uh, I think and
even more importantly, I think it's a
type of person that Kurt Cousins is.
He's he's a person with great character,
integrity, toughness. I always say when
I evaluate the quarterback position, two
non-negotiables for me, physical, mental
toughness. This guy has it. He doesn't
miss a lot of starts. Uh, I I think he
makes players around him better. Uh, and
I think he's going to be a real asset uh
to Fernando Mendoza because I think, you
know, that's going to be really
important when you start to build a
football team. That quarterback room is
is really the uh, you know, the
lifeblood of of your organization. And I
think having the right people in that
room is is so important.
>> Yeah. Yeah, I wanted to talk to you
about Fernando in a little bit, but
before that with Kirk joining the
Raiders as a first year head coach with
the Raiders and Clint Kubak and this is
Clint Kubak's sixth different team in
six straight years. They al they they
they crossed paths though back in
Minnesota, one of your former stomping
grounds as well and Andrew Janoko
coached him in Minnesota. How how clutch
is that to have that already that
familiarity? And I know the bones of it
are kind of the same when you're talking
about an offense and a scheme, but just
to have that familiarity with the scheme
coming in for a first year head coach to
have a veteran like him that already
kind of knows him and and and vice
versa.
>> Well, I think it's really important,
Paul, as you said. I I think there's
some history there, right? So, you know,
I think from the players perspective,
you know who you're dealing with with
the coach. I I always believe that that
relationship between quarterback and
coach is so important, right? you have
to know that that uh that that he trusts
you, that he's going to be there for
you, that he's going to have your back
in a critical situation and vice versa.
And I think so ha having some history
together is important. Also, when you're
trying to learn a new system, right, uh
the coach, I think, has an advantage. He
knows we've these are things we've done
in the past. I know what he likes. Uh I
know what he's good at. I know what he
has a history of doing. Uh and so when
we start putting together game plans, we
we kind of know that. And I think from
Kirk's perspective, you know, you you've
been in that quarterback room with him.
U you know, I think you I think I think
when you look at Clint Kubak, I think he
sees the game through the eyes of a
quarterback. Obviously, his dad was a
quarterback. And so I think that's
really important. And um I I just think
that you know the the other thing I've
known about Kirk Cousins and a lot of
people don't know this but he has spent
uh a good portion of the last couple off
seasons traveling to Tampa on his own
dime and spending some time with my
former coach John Gruden.
>> Yeah.
>> And uh he's put a lot of time in to get
better at his craft. And he's he's he's
at the facility. He's learning this new
offense. Um you know he's he's a guy
that's going to be totally committed.
And that's really what you want when
you're when you're again when you're
starting over. You want players that uh
realize the the importance of the
offseason program are going to be there
every day uh and they're going to try
and help build what what what we what we
know can be a championship organization.
Once again,
>> it's an interesting uh decision for Kirk
to come to the Raiders because there's
plenty of teams that had open spots to
be a starting quarterback and that did
not have the number one overall pick,
right? But he chose to come here. He
said in his press conference that his
gut told him to come here. What do you
see his role being in there? I mean, is
he a day one starter? Is he just a
mentor? Is he a little bit of everything
depending upon where the Raiders go? How
do you see his role kind of fleshing out
here as the season goes on?
>> Well, I in knowing him and and what I
would advise him is that he needs to
come in there and compete day one. And,
you know, don't worry about who gets
drafted, when they get drafted, what the
quarterback room. My job is to be
prepared and I'm going to compete. Uh I
think by competing uh you're going to
make everyone in that room better. Uh if
we were able, we're so fortunate to be
able to get Fernando Mendoza in the
draft, which I think we will, uh you
know, I want there to be competition,
right? I think, you know, in terms of
what the spring and summer looks like, I
would imagine that Mendoza is going to
get just about all the reps. We want to
get him as many reps as possible. Why?
because Kirk Cousins doesn't need a lot
of reps in in May, June, and July. He
doesn't. So, we want to get the young
rookie up to speed and we want to give
him as many reps as possible. And then
at that point, when we get into the
preeason, we can decide, okay, this
kid's ready to play or you know what,
maybe he's not ready to play week one.
Let's go with the veteran and let's find
a way to eventually work him into the
lineup. But, you know, it's there's no
timetable. It's not like we have to
decide tomorrow who the starter, you
know, I've heard a lot of Raider fans,
who's going to start week one? Who
cares? It doesn't matter right now.
Yeah. Like, we'll get to that. Let's
let's let's let's get as many good
players as we can on the football team.
Starting with that quarterback room.
We've already got Kirk Cousins. That's a
that's a big get. And now, if we can we
can we can get the pick we want in the
draft. Now, all of the sudden, we we
start to feel like that room's starting
to come together. And now, let's let
them compete and let's see where the
chips fall. But I think it's a great
situation for Clint Kubak and the staff
to be in when you start having some some
depth and talent. That that's really
when you look around the division. I
mean, you got Shawn Peyton and Bo Nicks
in Denver. You've got Justin Herbert and
Jim Harbaugh in Los Angeles. And you got
Andy Reid and Patrick Mahomes in Kansas
City. If you don't have a flamethrower
in this business, this is a bad business
to be in. And now we're starting to
really, I think, build really build and
address that quarterback room. And I'm
excited.
>> Rich, you know, the NFL calendar being
what it is, the the Raiders began their
offseason workouts in the in the
facility uh this week. Uh OTAAS are
upcoming. With that being said, I'd like
to play you a quick clip here of uh what
uh Kurt Cousins said about OTAAS.
>> Building relationship is a big deal. I
think it's hard in pro sports these days
with free agency and and you know, you
bring in 90 guys and you cut it down to
53. And so pro sports is not really
built to be together very long. And so
in college you had five years and um you
know the nucleus of the team was
together for a long time but in today's
you know pro sports world you have to
really you know find a way to kind of
pull together quickly and so it's even
more challenging as a leader as a
relationship builder to do that on a
shortened amount of time and um in a in
a shortened window. But uh that's that's
that's the goal and the challenge and I
think we play better and we're more
likely to win if we are playing together
and we do know each other well. So
that's something that OTAAS is about is
getting around each other and certainly
the X's and O's and the body work are
important, but I think the relationship
building is right up there as one of the
pillars of why we want to be here and
getting the work in.
>> So Rich, I think I hear that clip and I
think back to when you sat down with
Lincoln Kennedy and myself and we talked
about when you first came to the Raiders
and how you said in those offseason
programs, yes, they were voluntary, but
you had a handful of guys that were
there and it was hard to be that to
build that camaraderie and that that
those relationships. How important is it
then going forward for these guys now
that you know it's voluntary but you got
a lot of guys coming in to building that
chemistry?
>> Well, in my opinion, it's not voluntary.
In other words, I understand what the
National Football League players
association and what the owners agree
to, but it is the offseason attendance
uh in the OTAAS, the mini camps and the
offseason program is essential to
building a championship football team.
It is essential. And that's why when I
was with the Raiders, like I tried to
make every offseason work out because
why? You're the leader of the football
team. You have to be in the building.
You have to be there every single day.
And I think when you have ground to make
up in the division, and we do, then you
have to outwork the competition. You
have to you have to ensure that every
player on your team is committed to the
process. And it starts day one. It
starts in the weight room. It starts on
the practice field when we're doing the
conditioning and running in the training
room when we're doing the extra work in
the film room. Uh when we're learning a
new system, there's a lot of new
learning that's taking place at the
facility in Las Vegas. I mean, every
moment that you can get with the
position coach is so important. And
that's why like offseason, the
offseason, that's where I really got
better. I got better at my craft in the
off seasonason in February and March and
April and May. That's really where my
game really improved. And that's that's
what I would tell not just the young
players, but the older players, the
veteran players, if it's important to
you and you really truly want to be a
Raider and win championships, get your
butt in the building every single day.
>> Makes sense. Totally makes sense. You
being a fourth round pick, I want to
kind of go back a little bit. your
journey into the NFL. Fourth round pick
of the Patriots. Like I said, they
already had Steve Grogan and uh Tony
Een, but they wanted you to switch
positions. You said no, they traded you
to Minnesota where Wade Wilson and Tommy
Kramer were waiting there for you. H how
would you describe that early part of
your journey and and also because I know
when you came to the Raiders, the story
of you and John Gruden uh hitting it off
was amazing because there's a story of
you guys going to a dinner at the
Mexican restaurant in Alama. you picked
up a six-ack of beer, went back to the
facility, drew up some plays, and the
rest was history. How, you know, just in
in the Reader Digest version, how would
you describe that journey just in and of
itself?
>> Yeah, that that's a true true story.
Actually, I came in for my my visit and
that's how how it ended. We we went back
to the facility late at night and
watched film into the wee hours of the
morning. But, you know, I think there's
a learning curve with every young
player. When I came out of Delaware in
1987, I had a lot to learn and I got a
chance to go to Minnesota and and learn
behind two veteran quarterbacks, both
that played in Pro Bowls. So, that was
important. Um, I I would say that
there's very few quarterbacks that can
come into our league and have immediate
success. There's not a lot of Dan
Marinos out there. Even Pton Manning
went three and 13 his first year and
threw more interceptions and touchdowns.
So, who knows what the learning curve is
going to be for, you know, Fernando
Mendoza, but there are there are going
to be growing pains. And I just I just
think that, you know, you got to find
out where the player is, right? And you
got to put them in position where they
have a chance to be successful. You
don't want to ever throw him out there
before he's ready. You don't want to put
him out there behind a bad offensive
line, a running game that's not very
good. You got to put the player, that's
your job as a coach, to put the players
in a position where they have a chance
to succeed. John Gruden did that with me
when I first got to the Raiders. I knew
that system very well, but I spent a lot
of time in that building. And that's
what it's going to take, not just for
the at the quarterback position, but for
every position. We need leaders in every
room that are committed to excellence
and doing the work necessary to get this
thing turned around. I am excited. I am
tired of talking about it. I'm tired of,
you know, uh, you know, making excuses.
It's time to put up or shut up. We've
got a new coaching staff. We're going to
have a lot of new players. And, uh, I'm
excited for what what lies ahead in
2026.
>> You got me fired up, too, Rich. And I
want to close out with this. On Tuesday,
when uh Fernando was actually in the
building on his top 30 visit, I'm down
in the meal room and I feel this
presence behind me. I turn to look and
and Fernando Mendoza goes walking this
way. Then about a minute and a half
later, I see Kirk Cousins bounding
across the front of the the cafeteria
this way with the biggest grin on his
face. A minute or two later, Tom Brady
kind of comes floating by. You know,
just kind of that presence that he has.
How big is that going to be if it is
indeed for Nano Mendoza to have those
kinds of resources at his disposal? A
Kurt Cousins, a Tom Brady, you whatever
the the case may be. How huge is that
for a young guy coming in the league?
>> You know, I had a chance to visit with
him at the Super Bowl. Uh Fernando
Mendoza, first of all, there's a lot to
like there. I talk about physical,
mental toughness. He checks the box.
He's got size. He's almost 6'5. He's 235
pounds. I mean, he's built like a, you
know, Josh Allen or or Justin Herbert.
So, you like that about him. he can
create and manufacture offense on his
own. Um I I think he's a high character
uh great leader. I mean there there's a
lot of when you look at the qualities
and intangibles that you're looking for
at that position, he checks most of the
boxes. So I I just think I'm excited
about him. I'm excited about the the
potential there. And I'm also excited
about him being with the Tom Brady uh as
much as he possibly can because you know
Tom was a grinder. and Kirk Cousins, you
know, who watches a ton of film, who
works at it, you know, studies the
playbook. Um, football's important to
him. I think learning the right way when
you come in, uh, it's nice to have
mentors. It's nice to have people that
have gone before you than that have done
it. And I've talked to him at the Super
Bowl about what what it takes to play at
this level. He's going to hear from a
lot of different people. He's got a lot
of people in his corner, which I think
is a positive. And I I think he's a a
guy that's open to coaching. Uh, he
wants to get better. He wants to learn.
He wants to be coached hard and uh I
can't wait to see him in silver and
black.
>> Rich, always good to see you in silver
black as well and always great to catch
up. Thank you so so much for your time.
>> Thanks Paul.
>> So that'll do it for this week's edition
of Upon Further Review. Want to give our
thanks to our guest Rich Ganon for
reviewing all the recent news going on
with the Raiders. To stay up toate on
all things Silver and Black, you can
visit the Raiders YouTube channel and
raiders.com for more content.